בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody, should be a meaningful עשרה בטבת Asara
B'teves to one and all.
We start with the fourth פרק perek of מסכת עדות, Masechet Edus,
moving on from the question about the mechanisms of שבועות Shvuos and
to, I mean the mechanisms
how one taking effect on top of the other, negating a מצווה,
mitzvah, what שקר, sheker, what שווא, shav, etc. to more the use
of a שבועה shvua in a legal context. A between, the most
immediate thing that occurs to us is between litigants, but our פרק
perek is also about using a שבועה shvua to force people to
come and testify, a type of a what's that called, summons I
guess, or what's it called, subpoena. But before we say that I
today wanted to say one thing that we addressed yesterday and this
is sort of the downside of trying to use
the הלכה בדרך Halacha B'derech app, which is an amazing app, is
that in the רמב"ם Rambam part it doesn't have ראב"ד. Ra'avad. And
I wanted to just use a minute to repeat this because it
was an important idea, an idea that I've been repeating from the
very beginning is that the idea of a שבועה shvua as opposed
to a נדר neder is that a שבועה shvua is an implicit
or explicit invoking of God's name: לא תשא שם ה' אלהיך לשוא,
Lo tisa shem Hashem Elokecha lashav, לא תשבעו בשמי לשקר. lo tishavu
bishmi lashaker.
That's why for example there's a prohibition and even getting lashes for
a שבועת שווא shvuas shav but not for a נדר שווא. neder
shav. A נדר שווא neder shav is ay you try to make
something forbidden and it didn't become forbidden, who cares? But a שבועת
שווא shvuas shav you're invoking God's name for naught, right? And that's
why it's about the past and taking about actions, it's all about
invoking God's name. So the question becomes what about if you didn't
invoke God's name? You just said שבועה shvua I won't do A,
B, and C. So רמב"ם Rambam rules that if you don't invoke
God's name, there's no קרבן, korban, there's no מלקות malkus and so
on. Okay, now it could even one could even say in the
רמב"ם Rambam maybe it's all rabbinic, or maybe it's biblical but there's
no none of the punishments. Okay, but anyway that's what רמב"ם Rambam
says. So what I didn't get a chance to do is to
read you the ראב"ד. Ra'avad. Okay, because
רמב"ם's Rambam again language of this was in the beginning of שבועות,
Shvuos, פרק ב' perek bet הלכה ד': halacha daled:
if somebody says something ולא הזכיר שם, velo hizkir shem, didn't mention
God's name ולא כינוי, velo kinuy, הרי זה אסור בדבר שנשבע עליו,
harei zeh assur bedavar shenishba alav, the שבועה shvua is binding, אבל
אין לו מלקות ולא מביא קרבן. aval ein lo malkus velo meivi
korban. Okay,
but you don't get lashes and you don't bring a קרבן. korban.
So it might there's no consequence, again maybe who knows up in
heaven. Okay, but it might even be rabbinic, it's not clear on
the רמב"ם Rambam if there's no explicit name of God. ראב"ד Ra'avad
disagrees and ראב"ד Ra'avad says, and I just wanted to read this
because again it's just so important to understanding שבועות, Shvuos, ראב"ד Ra'avad
says that this isn't true, this might be by certain types of
שבועות, shvuos,
he says
אלא בעדות ובפקדון. ella be'edus uvifikadon. Interestingly ראב"ד Ra'avad says when does
שם ה' shem Hashem matter? Exactly around the issues we're going to
be talking about when it comes to a שבועה shvua about that
you don't know testimony or a שבועה shvua of a שומר shomer
that you're claiming what has happened to the object and so on,
that's where he says we find the idea of God's name and
he gives the various גמרות Gemaras what that's based on. He says
אבל בשבועת ביטוי, aval bishvuas bituy, a שבועה shvua that's about here's
what I'm going to do in the future or you're claiming about
something in the past maybe that, okay,
or a שבועת שווא, shvuas shav, everything we've learned until now, אפילו
מבטא או איסור שבועה afilu mifta o issur shvua you might remember
that from the גמרא, Gemara, even if you said מבטא mifta I
won't do this, שבועה shvua I won't do this, and it sounds
like even without using God's name, okay, אף
על פי שלא אמר לא שם ולא כינוי af al pi shelo
amar lo shem velo kinuy even if you didn't say God's name
or a another whatever not even the י-ה-ו-ה yud-keh-vav-keh but in a
different version of God's name. אם אמר Im amar wait a minute
ולא הזכיר שם, lo hizkir shem, וכן
וכן vechen vechen he goes further and he
says לא לא והן הן, lav lav vehen hen, if somebody says
yes yes I'll do this, no no I won't, the גמרא Gemara
says that's a type of a שבועה, shvua, again that most likely
is very much rabbinic, okay, and then he goes on and he
says so he says in all those
cases וכן ימין ושמאל, vechen yamin usmol, אם נתכוון לימין ושמאל הבורא
שבועה, im nitkaven l'yamin usmol haborei shvua, if you say by the
right hand and by the left hand and you mean like by
God's right hand okay but you never said it out loud, anyway
ראב"ד Ra'avad says there's all these different languages that are שבועה shvua
languages and from the גמרא Gemara it seems clearly you didn't say
God's name and it seems
clearly the גמרא Gemara seems to treat it like a full-fledged שבועה.
shvua. Now רמב"ם Rambam would also agree to all those things, he
would just say there's no מלקות, malkus, there's no קרבן korban etc.
again maybe it's rabbinic but ראב"ד Ra'avad says no no it sounds
like it's a real שבועה. shvua. Okay but now the ראב"ד Ra'avad
doesn't really what's all of a very, very long ראב"ד Ra'avad he
doesn't fully disagree with רמב"ם. Rambam. Here's the last line he says
which is very interesting: והני מילי לקרבן, v'hani milei lekorban, all of
that is in terms of a קרבן korban if a person
says... Why? He says,
also for the transgression of בל יחל דברו. Bal Yachal Devaro. It's
too bad Michael isn't here, that's what he was asking. You don't
need the idea of שם השם Shem Hashem for an idea of
creating an obligation, violating it, לא יחל דברו. Lo yachal devaro. Same
thing by a נדר. Nedar. נדר Nedar is not about שם השם.
Shem Hashem. It creates a reality about the object, you violated it,
it's לא יחל דברו. Lo yachal devaro. A שבועה Shevuah creates a
reality of an obligation upon you, a self-imposed obligation. Forget God's name.
You've created a self-imposed obligation, you violated it. That's an idea of
a קרבן Korban or לא יחל דברו. Lo yachal devaro. Okay, for
those two, yes, it is a total שבועה. Shevuah. But here is
where he agrees with רמב"ם. Rambam. He says, אבל למלקות, Aval le-malkus,
to get lashes, what do you have to transgress to get lashes?
You have to transgress לא תשא את שם השם אלוהיך לשוא, Lo
sisa es shem Hashem Elokecha lashav, of שבועת שוא. Shevuas shav. לא
תשבעו בשמי לשקר, Lo sishavu bishmi lashaker, of שבועת שקר. Shevuas sheker.
Those are about God's name. He says, אבל למלקות בעינן שם, Aval
le-malkus be'inan shem, דכתיב לא תשא את שם השם אלוהיך לשוא. de-ksiv
Lo sisa es shem Hashem Elokecha lashav. ושבועת שקר נמי לא תשבעו
בשמי לשקר. Ve-shevuas sheker nami lo sishavu bishmi lashaker. So ראב"ד Ra'avad
actually says there are two types, aspects, to a שבועה. Shevuah. A
שבועה Shevuah about God's name, yes, when it comes to the prohibitions
around a שבועה, Shevuah, not to take God's name in vain, not
to swear falsely by God's name. Those are about God's name. Without
God's name, you won't get lashes. Again, that's why a שבועת שוא
Shevuas shav you get lashes and not a נדר שוא, Nedar shav,
because a שבועת שוא Shevuas shav is about God's name in vain.
Okay, but even without God's name, the same way you can create
a נדר Neder and create a metaphysical reality about a status of
an object, you can create a metaphysical reality about a שבועה Shevuah
that obligates you even without it being God's name being a part
of that equation. Okay? And the consequence would be a קרבן, Korban,
or to transgress when it's a future-oriented שבועה, Shevuah, to transgress לא
יחל דברו. Lo yachal devaro. The same way by a נדר Neder
you transgress לא יחל דברו. Lo yachal devaro. Okay, so I thought
that was really worth taking a few minutes to just mention that
as a nice way of, you know, again, wrapping up that aspect
of God's name as central to שבועה, Shevuah, but ראב"ד Ra'avad sort
of has two components. But anyway, moving on to שבועת העדות, Shevuas
Ha-eidus, ראב"ד Ra'avad says, there I agree with רמב"ם. Rambam. שבועת העדות
Shevuas Ha-eidus does require God's name presumably even when a קרבן Korban
is involved. So now with that in mind, we'll use that as
our transition, let's take a look at the next פרק, Perek, which
is about שבועת העדות. Shevuas Ha-eidus. So starting from the top of
ל"א ע"א. Lamed Aleph Amud Aleph. Okay, שבועת העדות נוהגת באנשים ולא
בנשים. Shevuas ha-eidus noheges ba-anashim ve-lo ve-nashim. The שבועת העדות Shevuas Ha-eidus
applies to men and not women because it's all about you claim
to somebody, come and testify for me. And again, if the person
says, "Yes, I know testimony and I won't testify," that's not the
שבועת העדות Shevuas Ha-eidus in the תורה. Torah. The שבועה, Shevuah, I
mean, that's a שבועה לבטל את המצוה. Shevuah levatel es ha-mitzvah. The
שבועת העדות Shevuas Ha-eidus in the תורה Torah is when you deny
you know testimony, because it only is in contexts where your testimony
is relevant. So therefore it has to be about men and not
women, somebody who can testify in court. ברחוקים ולא בקרובים, Bi-rechokim ve-lo
bi-kerovim, only when you're asking somebody who's not a relative to you.
בכשרים ולא בפסולים, Bi-kesherim ve-lo bi-pesulim, only somebody who is a כשר
Kasher person to testify, let's say not a
גזלן. Gazlan. ואינו נוהגת אלא בראוין להעיד. Ve-eino noheges ela be-re'uyin le-ha'id.
It only applies to people that are fit to testify. Now it
seems like we just covered that. So who else is included by
that catch-all phrase? We'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. Oh, that's interesting,
maybe a minor or somebody who's not of like sound mind. That's
interesting, we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, בפני בית דין ושלא בפני בית דין. Bifnei beis din ve-shelo
bifnei beis din. Now רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir שיטה, Shittah, as we
saw quoted yesterday, is it would apply even if it was imposed
on somebody outside of court, right? So therefore, perhaps part of this
is schlepping somebody to get into the court building. Okay, מפי עצמו.
Mi-pi atzmo.
That's if the guy takes the oath himself, even outside of court,
it would be relevant. Now again, what do we mean it applies?
Just like the previous פרק, Perek, our primary frame of reference is
the קרבן Korban in the תורה. Torah. Okay? When do you bring
this קרבן Korban that the תורה Torah says if you took an
oath about testimony and you're lying about it? Okay? And interestingly, as
we're going to see in a minute, here it's even if you're
willfully lying about it. So the primary focus is קרבן. Korban. Could
there also of course be a מלקות Malkus if in a case
of let's say somebody did it במזיד? Be-mazid? Well, that's interesting, right?
So you might remember we had a discussion before that a שבועת
העדות Shevuas Ha-eidus could be that once the תורה Torah created this
category, it took it out of the classic category of the other
types of שבועות. Shevuos. Alright, so 'cause a classic case would be
that you're swearing that you don't know testimony, you're lying, if you
bring a קרבן, Korban, but why shouldn't you also be getting מלקות?
Malkus? Isn't that a שבועת שקר Shevuas sheker that you're willfully doing
and so on? Alright, so that's something to think about, but the
basic framework here is a קרבן Korban framework. Alright, so רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says that's when it's outside of
בית דין. Beis Din. ובין מפי עצמו ובין מפי אחרים, U-vein mi-pi
atzmo u-vein mi-pi acherim, I'm sorry, מפי עצמו. Mi-pi atzmo. מפי אחרים,
Mi-pi acherim, now, but if it's imposed by other people, אינו חייב
עד שיכפור בבית דין, eino chayav ad she-yichpor be-veis din, then it
has to be in court. You can't do to somebody outside of
court. דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what Meir says. You
might remember that we learned yesterday that if you said אמן Amen
outside of court, even though somebody else imposed it on you, it
would be like you took it yourself. Okay, so רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir has a שבועה shvua outside of court if you said it
yourself. And then that would be a type of a שבועת העדות
shvuas eidus to bring a קרבן. korban. Okay,
but חכמים אומרים, Chachamim omrim, but the sages say בין מפי עצמו
ובין מפי אחרים, bein mipi atzmo uvein mipi acherim, I don't care
if you said it yourself or other people imposed it on you,
אינם חייבין עד שיכפרו בבית דין. einam chayavim ad sheyichperu b'veis din.
This only takes place in the context of a court. Okay, where
you are in a context in which if you knew testimony, your
testimony would immediately be relevant. Here I am in court, I get
Charlie on the stand, and Charlie said, I don't know what you're
talking about, and I try to get him to testify what he
knows and he denies it. In that type of a context, it's
a real
denying of relevant testimony in a place where we need that testimony.
That's where the שבועת העדות shvuas eidus applies. Outside of the court,
yes, do I still need Charlie to come to court? Sure. But
he's not denying it like immediately in the context of where it
would be beneficial, right? It's like we're a stage removed from that
context. Okay, so therefore that according to the חכמים, Chachamim, even if
he takes the שבועה shvua himself, now that's interesting, would it be
a שבועת שקר, shvuas sheker, would it be a שבועת... shvuas... would
it be a different type of a שבועה? shvua? But it's not
the category of שבועת העדות shvuas eidus when it's not in the
context of court. Which by the way means for the חכמים Chachamim
and to some degree for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir too, because he...
because you can't... because it's... because he... because you can't
impose it on somebody else, this שבועה shvua is not... does not
work like I said before, does not work as a type of
a subpoena, right? Does not work to get somebody to court. I
come and tell you guys, yes, I borrowed money, you know, from
Michael, and they say, do you have a witness? I say, yeah,
חנן. Chanan. And they tell me, well, you know, that's only one
witness, we need two witnesses. I say, well, also Charlie. So then
they have to figure out how to shlep Charlie to court, right?
Like, I'm not going to be able to force Charlie, right, to...
you know, to take a... you know, outside... outside of... you know,
of court. If I go and I say, Charlie, come testify, and
he says, I don't know what you're talking about, I say, משביעך
אני. Mashbi'acha ani. As long as he's smart enough not to say
אמן, Amen, okay, then even according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that
שבועה shvua won't be effective on him. Alright, so therefore בית דין
Beis Din has to use whatever tools it has at its disposal
to bring Charlie to court and only there is my שבועה shvua
going to be able to then, like, force him to actually, you
know, say what I think he knows. Okay, but we have to
get him in the building to begin with. Okay,
so now it says like this, וחייבין על זדון השבועה ועל שגגתה
עם זדון העדות. v'chayavin al zadon hashvua v'al shiggasah im zadon ha'eidus.
Now, as I said before, the Torah here does not say ונעלם
ממנו. v'ne'elam mimenu. So this actually is an unusual קרבן korban that
you bring even if the person is willfully lying, זדון השבועה. zadon
hashvua. So Charlie swears falsely and he knows exactly what he is
doing, but he really hates me, he doesn't want to testify on
my behalf, or Michael's paid him off a few hundred dollars, whatever
the case might be. Okay, even though it's very conscious lying with
a שבועה, shvua, there's still a קרבן korban because it doesn't say
ונעלם ממנו. v'ne'elam mimenu. Or it could be, that's זדון השבועה, zadon
hashvua, ועל שגגתה עם זדון העדות, v'al shiggasah im zadon ha'eidus, or
it could be that he knows that he is lying, he's... he
knows about that he knows the testimony and he's claiming he doesn't,
that's זדון העדות, zadon ha'eidus, he's willful about that, but there's a
שוגג shogeg as far as it relates to the קרבן, korban, this
says a שוגג shogeg as far as it relates to the שבועה.
shvua. Meaning he knows he's lying, but he doesn't think, let's say,
that it's... that there's a prohibition about swearing falsely about it. Yes,
I know the testimony, yes, I know I'm lying, he's saying in
his own mind, but he doesn't think that he's transgressing, or that's...
that's שגגת שבועה, shiggas shvua, זדון העדות, zadon ha'eidus, you know the
testimony and you know you're lying about it, but you're שוגג shogeg
about the שבועה. shvua. You don't think maybe it's prohibited. Or the
case the גמרא Gemara prefers to go to, you know it's prohibited
to... to make a false שבועה, shvua, but you don't think that
there's a קרבן korban associated with it. So it's quite interesting, that
counts as a שוגג. shogeg. But why not? But here you don't
even need שוגג, shogeg, and the real question is why doesn't it
give the better example of שוגג? shogeg? What's the more obvious example
of שוגג? shogeg? If Charlie took an oath that he didn't know
testimony and I said he was a שוגג shogeg about it, what
would I most likely say? It means that he did know testimony
but he had forgotten it. But guess what? That's not a false
oath. Remember we said before, if you think you're telling the truth
when you take a שבועה shvua and you actually, you know, you're...
yes, I guys, I'm going to swear that I had eggs for
breakfast, and I got confused this morning, I got confused because actually
this morning I didn't eat anything, it's a תענית, Taanis, I was
thinking about yesterday, but in my mind, in my mind, I thought
I was telling the truth, it's not like I made a false
oath בשוגג, b'shogeg, it's not even a false oath. If you actually
believe you're telling the truth, we learned that before. So you can't
have a classic example of שוגג. shogeg. So the sho- because then
it wouldn't be- no קרבן, korban, no harm, no foul. The example
is you know you're lying and if you know you're lying and
you know it's אסור assur and there's a קרבן, korban, you're considered
a full מזיד mazed and you still bring a קרבן. korban. And
if you don't know it's אסור, assur, you don't know there's a
קרבן, korban, you're a שוגג shogeg and you would bring a קרבן
korban there too as long as you know you're lying, yes. So
what you just described there is similar to perjury because perjury... So
what you just described there is similar to perjury because perjury requires
intent to deceive. Oh, that's a good point. Right. And you're only
if you're just simply mistaken. Right, that's a good point. So in
this context that really works where we're talking about עדות, eidus, although
this point is true about שבועות shvuos in general, even when it's
not about a court or deceiving, but yes. Is this criminal or
civil? Both. Both? Yeah, but
זוממין zomemin is the is you testify falsely. Here you're trying to
avoid testifying altogether. But you're right, it's like the flip side of
it. Yeah, exactly. Well to follow up on that, we're not talking
about giving false testimony. Correct. We are about falsely claiming in the
presence of a court through an oath that you do not know
testimony. But as if you give false... if you give false testimony,
then you get off the... well, then you get off the hook.
There's a question about if you get מלקות malkus because, hey, how
do we even prove that it's false if you're not זוממין? zomemin?
Right, even if people contradict you, we sort of don't know who's
telling the truth or not. That gets to the whole discussion in
מכות, Makkos, okay? I mean, I guess we could sort of say,
let's say you say so-and-so got murdered and then he walks in,
right? So that's... you know, that would be an interesting case. But
right, but generally, you know, anyway, in theory there might be a
מלקות malkus for the איסור issur of false testimony, although often that's
played out in the context of עדים זוממין. eidim zomemin. Do you
have to give a שבועה shvua when you're testifying? No, you do
not have to give a שבועה shvua when you're testifying, which is
actually interesting, right? That's a good... it's worth mentioning that because in
all the cases about court, right, which we know through the media
or if we've ever been there, right, you know that a person
either swears or affirms that they're about to tell the truth, right?
So it's a very good and really worth mentioning, right, that that
is absolutely correct. שבועות shvuos occur between litigants or שבועה shvua occurs
if somebody doesn't want to get on the stand to testify and
therefore you make them take an oath that they don't know testimony,
so sort of it almost... the שבועה shvua is used to compel
testimony. But if somebody willfully gets on the stand and testifies, right,
no שבועה. shvua. And what they could be is if they're lying
they could be עדים זוממין, eidim zomemin, okay? Yes. So if
this person's withholding testimony causes a capital punishment, is there a punishment
from heaven as well as this? Right. Yeah, I mean, you know,
there's definitely ways in which you could passively or actively, but here
it would be passively, be a type of a גורם gorem and
a contributor to somebody being, you know, having money taken away from
them or being punished when they didn't deserve to be punished, suffering
when they didn't deserve... yeah, sure, you know, I'll trust God to
even up the account. But yes, you know, alright. So it says,
okay. I mean, the גמרא Gemara even talks... the גמרא's Gemara discussion
about חייב בידי שמים chayav bidei shamayim is more active. If somebody
hires witnesses to testify falsely, so the witnesses are עדים זוממין eidim
zomemin and they could get killed or whatever, let's say in a
capital case. The person who hires them, okay, he's being very active,
he's, you know, he's the one organizing the whole thing, it says
he's פטור בדיני אדם וחייב בידי שמים. patur bidinei adam vechayav bidei
shamayim. Like as far as heaven is concerned, he committed murder even
though we won't do it. Okay, so that's like considered because he's
so active or whatever, that's like he committed murder, except, except, you
know, God will take care of it, not down here. The רמב"ם
Rambam actually calls such a person a רוצח, rotzeach, a murderer. He
says, אלו הם הרוצחים, eilu heim harotzchim, the רמב"ם Rambam says. But
anyway, somebody who passively doesn't speak up and as a result somebody's
going to be executed also has his share of responsibility but it's
not the same degree. Okay, so then it says ואינם חייבים אלא
על שיגגתה, ve'einam chayavim ela al shigegatah,
but if it's a full שוגג shogeg you don't bring a קרבן.
korban. A full שוגג shogeg means you thought you were telling the
truth, okay? ומה הן חייבין על הזדון? umah hein chayavin al hazadon?
That should be on זדון השבועה, zadon hashvua, because actually זדון השבועה
zadon hashvua we don't want to limit it to זדון השבועה, zadon
hashvua, it's even זדון העדות. zadon haeidus. What are you obligated if
you are willfully lying, whether you are knowing you're doing an עבירה
aveira or not, but if you're willfully lying what do you bring?
קרבן עולה ויורד. korban oleh veyored. Okay, a קרבן korban goes up
and down, seemingly presumably no
מלקות malkus even though you did a total willful חטא. cheit. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: מנא הני מילי? mena hanei
milei? Where's this from? To where's what from? Interestingly of all... of
everything in the משנה mishna the גמרא Gemara chooses to focus in
on the fact that אנשים ולא נשים. anashim velo nashim. How do
you know that women can't testify? That's going to be the primary
focus of the גמרא. Gemara. מנא הני מילי? mena hanei milei? דתנו
רבנן detanu rabanan we taught: ועמדו שני האנשים אשר להם הריב לפני
ה', ve'amdu shnei ha'anashim asher lahem hariv lifnei Hashem,
the two people who have the fight stand before God. So presumably
the two people who have the fight mean it's the two litigants,
okay? But the גמרא Gemara says since it mentions two, classic two
people standing up in a court case are witnesses. בעדים הכתוב מדבר,
be'eidim hakatuv medaber,
witnesses. And therefore, what it doesn't even tell you is what's the
point of quoting this because it says האנשים, ha'anashim, the men. So
therefore we read, אה, ועמדו שני
האנשים, ah, ve'amdu shnei ha'anashim, so these are the witnesses and they're
described as men. And therefore you can only have men as witnesses.
An interesting תוספות, Tosafos, the last תוספות Tosafos of the previous פרק
perek
discusses the question, we're not going to read it but a common
theme that תוספות Tosafos discusses multiple times. can women be judges? Can
we assume that since they can't be witnesses they can't be judges?
What about the whole precedent with דבורה, Devorah, right? ששפטה את ישראל.
Sheshoftah et Yisrael. So that's an interesting thing, it's the last תוספות
Tosafot of the previous פרק. Perek. Alright, ועמדו שני האנשים אשר להם
הריב. Ve'amdu shnei ha'anashim asher lahem hariv.
You say it's witnesses, but maybe it's really talking about the litigants.
No, כשאומר אשר להם הריב, Keshe'omer asher lahem hariv,
it says the two people, the two men who have the fight.
So the who have the fight part of the phrase, or have
the dispute, I should say, that's the litigants. הרי בעלי דינים אמור.
Harei ba'alei dinim amur. המני מקיים ועמדו שני האנשים? Hamani mekayem ve'amdu
shnei ha'anashim?
What does the first part of the verse, the two men, refer
to? So בעדים הכתוב מדבר, Be'edim hakatuv medaber,
witnesses, and from there we learn witnesses have to be men. ואם
נפשך לומר, Ve'im nafshcha lomar,
and if you want, if you don't like that argument, I'll make
another argument. נאמר כאן שני, Ne'emar kan shnei, here it says two,
ונאמר להלן שני, Vene'emar lehalan shnei, it says על פי שני עדים,
Al pi shnei edim, right? So, or what's the פסוק? Pasuk? Right.
Yeah, על פי שני עדים יומת המת לא יומת על פי עד
אחד. Al pi shnei edim yumat hamet lo yumat al pi ed
echad. So there explicitly the word שני Shnei is used together with
עדים. Edim. מה להלן בעדים אף כאן בעדים. Mah lehalan be'edim af
kan be'edim. Okay, so that's the דרשה. Drasha. Either שני, Shnei, the
very word שני Shnei tells us witnesses, or just by separating it
from the first half of the פסוק, Pasuk, the second half is
talking about litigants, the first half is witnesses. מאי ואם נפשך לומר?
Mai ve'im nafshcha lomar? Why did we have to go to the
גזירה שוה Gezeirah Shavah of שני? Shnei? What was the matter with
the first approach? וכי תימא מדלא כתיב ואשר להם הריב, Vechi teima
midlo ketiv ve'asher lahem hariv, it was really talking about two sets
of people. It would have said ועמדו שני האנשים, Ve'amdu shnei ha'anashim,
the two people, i.e., the witnesses, that's the way you want to
read it, ואשר להם הריב, Ve'asher lahem hariv, and the people and
the litigants. Since it doesn't have a ו, Vav, it sounds like
it's all one description. The two people who have the dispute means
that all means the litigants. So I don't agree to use the
first half of the verse to refer to witnesses. So then כולי
קרא בבעלי דינים משתעי, Kulei kra beba'alei dinim mishta'ei, so you'll claim
the whole, the entire phrase is about the litigants. נאמר כאן שני
ונאמר להלן שני מה להלן בעדים אף כאן בעדים. Ne'emar kan shnei
vene'emar lehalan shnei mah lehalan be'edim af kan be'edim. So the שני
Shnei word signals that we're talking about witnesses and that's how we
know we're witnesses and that they have to be men. Okay, תניא
אידך, Tanya idach, another ברייתא. Braita. ועמדו שני האנשים בעדים הכתוב מדבר.
Ve'amdu shnei ha'anashim be'edim hakatuv medaber. אתה אומר בעדים או אינו אלא
בבעלי דינים? Atah omer be'edim o eino ela beba'alei dinim? You say
witnesses, maybe it's litigants. אמרת וכי שניים באים לדין שלושה אין באים
לדין? Amarta vechi shnayim ba'im ladin shlosha ein ba'im ladin? No, the
fact that it says two means a type of a thing in
which it's particularly about two people. So litigants, you could have multiple
litigants in a case. Okay, you can have the Hatfields and the
McCoys, you could have a lot of different parties there fighting stuff
out. Class action suit. So two, now of course you could have
three witnesses to something as well, but two is like a threshold,
two is like the core number by witnesses. And usually it's hard
to get two let alone three. Okay, so או אינו אלא בבעלי
דינים אמרת וכי שניים באים לדין שלושה אין באים לדין. O eino
ela beba'alei dinim amarta vechi shnayim ba'im ladin shlosha ein ba'im ladin.
ואם נפשך לומר, Ve'im nafshcha lomar, okay, so that's just the very
fact that it says two tells me not because of a גזירה
שוה, Gezeirah Shavah, but just because most likely we're talking about witnesses
and not litigants. ואם נפשך לומר, Ve'im nafshcha lomar, but if you
don't like that sort of logical argument, נאמר כאן שני ונאמר להלן
שני מה להלן בעדים אף כאן בעדים. Ne'emar kan shnei vene'emar lehalan
shnei mah lehalan be'edim af kan be'edim. The גזירה שוה. Gezeirah Shavah.
Okay, yes, it's still by two, but it's more because two is
a marked word, like it's a specific connected word. מאי ואם נפשך
לומר? Mai ve'im nafshcha lomar? Why wouldn't I have thought the first
argument was strong enough? וכי תימא בטובע ונתבע קא משתעי קרא. Vechi
teima betove'a venitba ka mishta'ei kra. Yes, it's true there could be
a lot of different people involved, but ultimately there are two parties.
There are the two parties. There's the defendant and the accused, the
person who's suing and the person who's being sued. So even if
it's 20 people in each party, they're conceptually there's still two. So
the same way witnesses have a number two associated with it, litigants
fundamentally have a number two associated. So therefore בטובע ונתבע הכתוב מדבר.
Betove'a venitba hakatuv medaber. נאמר כאן שני ונאמר להלן שני. Ne'emar kan
shnei vene'emar lehalan shnei. Fine, we'll use שני Shnei as a keyword
and שני Shnei links to the other שני Shnei that said specifically
by witnesses. מה להלן בעדים אף כאן בעדים. Mah lehalan be'edim af
kan be'edim. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we got a third ברייתא. Braita.
ועמדו שני האנשים בעדים הכתוב מדבר. Ve'amdu shnei ha'anashim be'edim hakatuv medaber.
אתה אומר בעדים או אינו אלא בבעלי דינים? Atah omer be'edim o
eino ela beba'alei dinim? You say it's witnesses and therefore witnesses have
to be men. Maybe it's talking about litigants. אמרת וכי אנשים באים
לדין נשים אינם באים לדין? Amarta vechi anashim ba'im ladin nashim einam
ba'im ladin? והא פסוק דדין. Veha pasuk dedin. Wait a minute. If
the whole point of אנשים Anashim we're going to use to say
only men and not women, that's how we know we can't be
talking about litigants. What, women never have a reason to bring a
case to court? They never have a reason to sue or to
be sued or whatever? And you could sort of ask it as
a public policy issue. Do we want to exclude women from the
ability to be litigants or defendants in court? So obviously if we're
going to say this word means men and not women, we're going
to want to interpret that phrase as being about witnesses and not
about litigants. Okay, so ואם נפשך לומר, Ve'im nafshcha lomar, and if
you don't like that דרשה, Drasha, so נאמר כאן שני ונאמר להלן
שני מה להלן בעדים אף כאן בעדים. Ne'emar kan shnei vene'emar lehalan
shnei mah lehalan be'edim af kan be'edim. We'll just learn it from
the word שני. Shnei. מאי ואם נפשך לומר? Mai ve'im nafshcha lomar?
Why wouldn't I like that דרשה? Drasha? Like presumably yeah, I mean
when the תורה Torah describes men, it might mean... funny to be
saying that to exclude women by coming to court. No, because here's
how I could have read it: וכי תימא אשה לאו אורחה, V'chi
teima ishah lav orcha, maybe a woman, maybe it's using the word
אנשים anashim maybe not to legally exclude women from being a litigant,
but maybe it's to sort of use the word because it's normal
for men to bring a case to court, and it's less common
to which we're describing a common case. A common case is that
the litigants are men. Why is it less common for a woman
to bring a case to court? משום, Mishum, here comes a פסוק:
pasuk: כל כבודה בת מלך פנימה. Kol kvuda bat melech pnima. The
whole honor of the daughter of the king is inside. Okay, so
therefore since women normally are more in the domestic sphere, not in
the public sphere, you know there's a whole interesting question, right, is
the גמרא Gemara sort of dictating this as the proper way in
which, you know, it's expected of women or whatever, or is it
just sort of describing societal norms? You know, this it's normal. But
anyway, so obviously those are things that, you know, that certainly get
debated nowadays. But but the basic point is is that the, what
do you call it, is that the תורה Torah could be saying
men not to exclude women from the role of litigants, but it
could be saying men from just describing the natural thing is that
men are bringing cases to court and not women. Yes, Charlie. The
woman in that verse is actually a non-Jew if you read the
entire פרק perek too. Okay, that's interesting. Okay, so now תוספות Tosafot
has an interesting question, which is as long as the use of
the word men might not be used as a legal term, but
as a descriptive, maybe it means that even if it's talking about
witnesses, maybe it's assuming witnesses are men because women stay home more,
not to legally exclude them. So look at תוספות: Tosafot: כל כבודה
בת מלך פנימה. Kol kvuda bat melech pnima. ואם תאמר השתא נמי
דאיירי בעדים מנא לן למעוטי נשים? V'im tomar hashta nami d'ayrei b'edim
m'na lan l'miutei nashim? And how do you know to use the
word men to exclude women? דילמא האי דנקט אנשים משום דכל כבודה
בת מלך. Dilma hai d'nakat anashim mishum d'kol kvuda bat melech. Maybe
it's talking about witnesses, but it's saying the normal case is that
men because women stay home more. ויש לומר דגבי עדים על כרחך
צריכין לבוא דאין עד מפי עד כשר. V'yesh lomar d'gabi edim al
korchacha t'richin lavo d'ein ed mipi ed kasher. No, because witnesses, if
women saw something, then they would have to come. There's no way
they could avoid their responsibility and stay home. The only way they
could stay home is if they know testimony is by shirking their
responsibility, because they can't tell somebody else oh here's what I saw,
tell their husband here's what I saw, go tell it in court.
That's not legal testimony. אבל לדין יכולה למסור טענותיה ביד אחר. Aval
l'din yechola limsor tanoteha b'yad acher. But if she had a court
case, okay,
as long as she wasn't the defendant, as long as she was
the litigant, but she can empower somebody else, give somebody else power
of attorney, and allow somebody else to bring her court case for
her. She wouldn't have to come herself. Okay, so therefore we could
accept that the פסוק pasuk would say that the, if it were
not making a legal point, just a descriptive point, it could say
the men as the litigants because it could sort of be saying,
you know, women would, even when they had cases, would often place,
you know, have them fought out through a male representative. They would
want to stay home, okay? But if it was describing witnesses, then
it's not,
then women would have to come just as much as men if
they knew testimony. I don't care you want to stay at home,
you like being private, okay? You're obligated to come. So if even
there it's going to say men, it's going to be understood as
a legal term. That's the way תוספות Tosafot understands it. Okay, so
back to the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: ועמדו שני האנשים.
V'amdu shnei ha'anashim.
So that's how we know women and not, men and not women.
Now because we're quoting this that the two men stand, we're going
to talk about how testimony is given, okay, ועמדו שני האנשים, v'amdu
shnei ha'anashim,
or testimony and how whatever, various procedures about the court case or
norms about the court case. ועמדו שני האנשים, V'amdu shnei ha'anashim, מצוה
לבעלי דינין שיעמדו. mitzvah l'ba'alei dinin she'ya'amodu.
So now we're
reading שני האנשים shnei ha'anashim in the פשט pshat of the פסוק
pasuk as the litigants and we're saying this is teaching you that,
you know, the judges sit and the litigants stand, okay? אמר רבי
יהודה שמעתי שאם רצו להושיב את שניהם מושיבין. Amar Rabbi Yehuda shamati
she'im ratzu l'hoshiv et shneihem moshivin.
Really there's no requirement technically that the litigants stand, okay, but the
point is don't show differential treatment. If the court wants to have
both of them sit, that's also fine, okay. איזו היא אסורה? Eizo
hi asura? What would be forbidden? שלא יהיה אחד עומד ואחד יושב.
Shelo yehei echad omed v'echad yoshev.
One standing and one sitting. אחד מדבר כל צרכו ואחד אומר לו
קצר דבריך. Echad medaber kol tzorcho v'echad omer lo katzer devarecha.
One person gets the opportunity to say everything he wants to say
and the other person they say, you know, speed it up buddy,
we're on the clock, okay? תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, and we learn
that from a פסוק, pasuk, that idea. בצדק תשפוט עמיתך. B'tzedek tishpot
amitecha. We learn that from ועמדו v'amdu because ועמדו v'amdu doesn't tell
us the problem of differential treatment. He says ועמדו, v'amdu, you know,
maybe that's like the norm would be to ask them to stand,
it's totally at the judge's discretion to have them sit, okay, but
we actually learn fair treatment and that actually we learn from elsewhere,
okay. So, תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: בצדק תשפוט עמיתך. B'tzedek tishpot amitecha.
With righteousness you should just judge your fellow. שלא יהיה אחד יושב
ואחד עומד. Shelo yehei echad yoshev v'echad omed. One person shouldn't stand
and one shouldn't sit. אחד מדבר כל צרכו ואחד אומר לו קצר
דבריך. Echad medaber kol tzorcho v'echad omer lo katzer devarecha. One person,
you know, they... they get the opportunity to speak all they want
and the other say, "would you please hurry up?" Now I would
like to make a point, I'm not sure it's exactly the point
the גמרא's Gemara making, but I think it is, which is: they're
not saying that you have to give if you give this guy
a half hour you have to give that guy a half hour.
They say if we gave one person a full time to say
what he says we have to give the other person.
Well you could imagine a certain person, some people are very articulate,
they're very focused, they can say exactly what they need to say
right up front. Other people like they're in a court, they're nervous,
whatever, it takes them time to get out what they need to
say, it feels like oh my god will you get to the
point already, right? So it could actually be that one guy needs
two hours to say what he needs to say and the other
guy only needs ten minutes, okay, and it's still saying you can't
tell the other guy, "do it in ten minutes." You need to
give the other guy the time that he needs. And I think
it's important the word בצדק B'tzedek because it's like the thing we
tell kids, like there's a difference between what is it, equality and
justice, right? So yes, I gave your brother this thing and I
didn't give it to
you, sometimes because you deserve the right thing to do is you
have different needs and different
realities and therefore different treatment is actually it's fair even though it's
not equal. Maybe that's what they say, the difference between being fair
and being equal, right? So it doesn't mean that if your brother
is two times as big as you that you get the same
size piece of pie for
example, right? So there's a difference between fairness and justice on one
hand and like equality on the other, total equal treatment. So anyway
I think that's important בצדק תשפוט עמיתך, B'tzedek tishpot amitecha, to make
sure that things are not necessarily like one size fits all, but
that they're fair and they're understanding the different circumstances. That's how I
would like to read it. Okay anyway, so תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan
we talked. בצדק תשפוט עמיתך B'tzedek tishpot amitecha we just did that.
דבר אחר, Davar acher, בצדק תשפוט עמיתך, B'tzedek tishpot amitecha, הוי דן
את חברך לכף זכות. Havei dan et chavercha l'chaf zechut.
So this is a sense of עמיתך Amitecha not in the context
of how the judges treat people in court, but your fellow, it's
normal types of social interactions. Judge your... when do I judge my
fellow? I'm not a judge who sits in a court case. No,
sadly some people judge other people all the time, right? You see
people doing something, you're very judgmental, you're always judging somebody and judging
usually means you're always judging them and finding fault with them, right?
A judgmental person doesn't mean I'm always judging somebody and finding they're
always coming out good. So anyway, so no, so it says when
you're judging your fellow, you shouldn't just say don't judge at all,
but
judge them, always tip to the scale of לכף זכות. L'chaf zechut.
A כף Kaf is like a pan, the pan they use on
a balance scale. לדון לכף זכות L'don l'chaf zechut means like
put your finger on the side of the balance that's the merit,
like tipping in favor of a sympathetic or generous interpretation of what
you're seeing, okay. So it's not like an innocence until proven guilty
thing? No, because this is not about the court, right? This is
like you're just looking at what somebody is doing, you can make
negative assumptions that would see that critically or you can make other
assumptions that would actually see that non-critically and sympathetically and so on.
Oh I'm sure he had a reason, I'm sure whatever, we probably
don't understand why he was doing that, right? So that's if you're
gonna judge your friend, be דן לכף זכות. Dan l'chaf zechut. תני
רב יוסף, Tani Rav Yosef, בצדק תשפוט עמיתך, B'tzedek tishpot amitecha, עם
שאתך בתורה ובמצוות. Im she'itcha b'Torah u'v'mitzvot. The עמיתך Amitecha your fellow
means עם שאתך, Im she'itcha, the one who is with you, meaning
somebody who is similarly observant as you are, okay. So what does
that mean? I don't have to be fair to somebody who's not
fully observant? So השתדל לדונו יפה. Hishtadel l'dono yafe. Judge them well.
What does judge them well mean? So רש"י Rashi says obviously that's
a little troubling, what does that mean, favoritism to somebody who's more
observant in court? So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi
says like five lines from the bottom השתדל לדונו יפה Hishtadel l'dono
yafe וקמפרש לה למישרי בתיגרא v'kamperash la l'mishrei b'tigre אם באו שני
דינים לפניך ואחד מהם של תלמידי חכמים הוי פוסק אותו תחילה ופוטרו
מלפניך. im bau sheni dinim lefanecha ve'echad mehem shel talmidei chachamim havei
posek oto techila u'potro milfanecha. Basically it's you let them like jump
the line or not jump the line whatever, meaning תוספות Tosafot says
not jump the line. If two people came to you at the
same time, two cases confronted you at the same time and you
had to pick one of them, you can choose to hear the
case of the תלמיד חכם. Talmid chacham. It's interesting רש"י Rashi doesn't
say observant versus non-observant, but emphasizing more the תורה Torah part as
opposed to the מצוות Mitzvot part. But anyway, for somebody who's more
your fellow in terms of commitment to תורה ומצוות, Torah u'mitzvot, you
can choose to judge them, to take their case before somebody else's,
but again רש"י Rashi says and תוספות Tosafot qualifies clearly only if
they came to you at the same time. If somebody came, the
other case came first, you can't have your friend or the really
observant person jump the line and get to the beginning of the
line just because they're observant. But if you have to choose and
they're both at the same time you can use this as a
basis, that's the way to limiting sort of the scope of what
the גמרא's Gemara saying. Yes, wasn't there discussion... Wasn't there discussion of
this similar issue regarding timing of funerals when two people die at
the same time? Yeah, that's true, but that's also an issue of
honor, so that's maybe a little different. Okay, in the context here
where we're talking about justice, you don't really want to be talking
about any favoritism in that context. So therefore, this idea of it's
ironic that judge them not favorably, judge them well, right. In other
words it's not saying oh if the guy's איתך בתורה ובמצוות itcha
batorah u'mitzvos judge him to find him innocent or judge him... it
didn't say favorably, it said judge him well. So it's an interesting
balance between that and that's actually the remainder of this דף daf
is the balance between giving honor and recognition of somebody's status, and
at the same time the whole point of the תורה Torah is,
right, כקטן כגדל תשמעון, kakatun kaggadol tishmaun, right, like the big one
like the small one, right, לא תכירו פנים במשפט, lo takiru fanim
bamishpat, don't give any recognition of status. It's supposed to be pure
justice. So here we shrink this to mean that it means basically
two cases I have to choose which one to hear first, fine,
in that limited situation I can pick the person who's איתך בתורה
ובמצוות. itcha batorah u'mitzvos. Okay, רב עולא בריה דרב עילאי הוה ליה
דינא קמיה דרב נחמן. Rav Ulla brei d'Rav Ilai havilei dina kamei
d'Rav Nachman. So Rav Ulla had a tort case in front of
Rav Nachman. שלח ליה רב יוסף, shalach lei Rav Yosef, so Rav
Yosef sent to Rav Nachman, עולא חברנו, Ulla chaveirenu, Ulla our friend,
our colleague, עמית בתורה ובמצוות. amit batorah u'mitzvos. The word עמית amit
is עמיתך amitcha from the verse. He's our friend when it comes
to תורה Torah and מצוות. Mitzvos. So he's about to go hear
your court case, you should know he's one of us. So that
doesn't... אמר ליה, amar lei, so אמר, amar, so Rav Nachman said,
למה שלח לי? Lama shalach li? Why is he sending it to
me? לחנפויי ליה? lachanfeyei lei? Does he just want to flatter this
guy? Like he obviously doesn't want to influence my judgment, so why
is he just סתם stam singing the praises of this litigant who's
appearing before me? He just wants to flatter him, what's the point?
הדר אמר, hadar amar, no, למישרא דקטריה. lemishra d'kitrei. It must mean
that if I have a choice between hearing which case... למישרא דקטריה
lemishra d'kitrei means to like undo his bonds or whatever, his fight,
meaning to get him out, you know, to sort of move him
along within a little פרוטקציה protexia here. Okay, I know the line
Bernie Shatz once told me many years ago, he says פרוטקציה protexia
doesn't matter as long as you know the right people. For you
know, when Devorah recently had an accident and whatever, she had to
go to the hospital, she had like, you know, all these people
who like, you know, called up ahead, basically she got there, she
didn't have to wait in the waiting room, she saw right to
a room, she saw three doctors within the first half hour, like
all the nurses wanted to know like, who are you? Are you
some celebrity? So you know, you know the right people. So anyway,
so that's what it does, you speed them along and again, תוספות
Tosafos says it's only if, you know, you didn't sort of encounter
another case first. תוספות Tosafos limits it to when they all came
at the same time. But anyway, fine, but it doesn't mean that
there's any favoritism in the actual court case itself. However, that being
said, we have the next line. אי נמי לשודא דדייני, inaami leshuda
de'dayni, or for a case where it's a judgment which is totally
at the discretion of the judge. Some cases the גמרא Gemara determines
that we have a it's a total toss-up where we're never going
to get more information, like for example, a case, you know, some
type of a gift is given and somebody writes in his will,
I'm giving it to ראובן בן שמעון Reuven ben Shimon and there's
two ראובן בן שמעון's Reuven ben Shimon in the city and we
have no way of knowing which one he referred to. So what
do you do with it? So it's the judge's discretion. Okay, so
there's an interesting debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafos. Does it
mean that the judge has to try to figure out to the
best he can who he most probably liked? Well, you know, I
know this guy was, you know, went to the... you know, liked
hiking and I heard that this ראובן בן שמעון Reuven ben Shimon
was a hiker. I have no evidence that they were friends, but
you know, who knows? Maybe there's a good reason to think maybe
that's the guy. Maybe he bumped into him hiking or something like
that. Okay, that's one way. You try to do the best you
can to figure out which one he means. Or the other explanation
is, no, you just decide as a public policy matter who would
you rather award it to? Okay, so for the second version, you
understand, if I get total discretion who to give it to, I'd
rather give it to somebody who's a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham than
somebody who's not a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. Okay, but so that
is actually a real case of favoritism, but it's in a very
narrow set of circumstances where we don't know how to conclude the
case and we give the judge like total discretion. Okay, so אמר
עולא, amar Ulla, now, back to this debate about do you have
to stand or not. מחלוקת בבעלי דינין. machlokes be'baalei dinin. The debate
about whether you have to stand is about litigants, where רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says you don't have to stand as long as you
treat them equally. Remember that's where we got onto this digression from.
אבל בעדים, aval be'eidim, when it comes to testifying, דברי הכל בעמידה.
divrei hakol be'amida. Everybody agrees the witnesses have to stand. דכתיב ועמדו
שני האנשים. dechtiv ve'amdu shenei ha'anashim. Okay, since שני האנשים shenei ha'anashim
here more as we learned, more means witnesses, and then we're going
to read the ועמדו ve'amdu in this context as very much, you
know, as like a, you know, as a real requirement when it
comes to witnesses. Of course raises interesting questions, you know, let's say
somebody's wheelchair-bound. Talk about the issue before between like justice and equality,
right? So you know, so really... Somebody can't testify even if they
don't have an option of standing, how much is this really מעכב
me'akev or not מעכב? me'akev? Okay, so let's take a look. Okay.
Where were we? Okay, so Gemara says like this. אמר רב הונא
מחלוקת בשעת משא ומתן, Amar Rav Huna machloket besha'at masa umatan, that
debate about the litigants is when the deliberations are going on. אבל
בשעת גמר דין, aval besha'at g'mar din, when the actual ruling is
being handed down, דברי הכל דיינים בישיבה ובעלי דין בעמידה. divrei hakol
dayanim biyashiva uba'alei din be'amida. Everybody agrees there that you have to
make it clear like the judges have a different status than the
litigants and the judges are passing sentence on the litigants. So in
that case, the judges sit and the litigants stand. You see this
in court cases, right? They say, please rise, for when the jury
comes back with its judgment. דכתיב וישב משה לשפוט את העם ויעמדו
העם על משה מן הבוקר עד הערב. dichtiv vayeishev Moshe lishpot et
ha'am vaya'amdu ha'am al Moshe min haboker ad ha'arev. He was sitting
and they were standing. לשון אחר מחלוקת בשעת משא ומתן. Lashon acher
machloket besha'at masa umatan. The issue is about during the deliberations. אבל
בשעת גמר דין דברי הכל דיינים בישיבה ובעלי דין בעמידה, aval besha'at
g'mar din divrei hakol dayanim biyashiva uba'alei din be'amida, same הלכה, halacha,
the judges sit and the litigants stand, but not based on the
verse by Moshe, based on דהעדים כגמר דין דמו, deha'edim k'gmar din
damu, because witnesses is like גמר דין. gmar din. Why is witnesses
like גמר דין? gmar din? Because like something actually, the accepting of
a, it sort of moves along the דין, din, it gives real
facts that now is going to whatever. The litigants are making different
claims, but it's not as much of a concrete fact that's being
presented to בית דין beis din that has almost like a compelling
consequence to it. And also there's like in halachic terms, there's like
a חלות chalos idea of קבלת עדות. kabbalas eidus. There's a formal
moment of קבלת עדות. kabbalas eidus. So anyway, because of the sort
of ritual almost moment of that, they have to stand. וכתיב ועמדו
שני האנשים. Uchtiv ve'amdu shenei ha'anashim. So therefore, when other people have
a when there's a real גמר דין, gmar din, you after also
have to stand. Okay. So now we have an interesting case going
dealing with all these issues about standing, but also giving honor to
תורה Torah status and interestingly, this is actually about a wife of
a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. So let's take a look. דביתהו דרב
הונא, Deviteihu deRav Huna, the wife of רב הונא Rav Huna after
it was after רב הונא Rav Huna had passed away, הוי לה
דינא קמיה דרב נחמן, havi lah dina kamey deRav Nachman, had a
court case in front of רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. אמר היכי נעביד,
Amar heichi na'avid, רב נחמן Rav Nachman said, how am I going
to treat this case when she walks into the room? אי אקום
מקמה, Ei akum mikama, I need to stand for her. It's interesting,
right? Here she is the widow of this great תלמיד חכם, talmid
chacham, but nevertheless the כבוד התורה kevod haTorah that is afforded to
that תלמיד חכם talmid chacham is afforded even to his widow even
after he passes away. Okay. So I need halachically to stand in
her presence. אבל אי עבידנא הכי מסתתמין טענתיה דבעל דינא. aval ei
avidna hachi mistatmin ta'antei deba'al dina. So the claims of her opposing
litigant will be stopped up, meaning the guy would go, oh, he
honors her not me or whatever. And even if he says, look,
it's not that I really treating her differently, I just have a
halachic obligation, like yeah, that's going to go really far. Like it
shows clearly you're showing respect and honor for one of the litigants.
Okay. So לא אקום מקמה, lo akum mikama, maybe I shouldn't rise
for her. אשת חבר הרי היא כחבר. Eshet chaver harei hi kechaver.
I'm not entitled to do that. The wife of a חבר, chaver,
even the widow, has to be treated like a חבר. chaver. So
what I don't understand is why didn't he just rise for both
litigants? Who's preventing him from rising? But maybe he would feel that
that would be a degrading of his own כבוד. kavod. Here he
is, he's a major תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, major judge, and some
layperson whatever walks in and I'm going to rise up for them?
Like that's like disgracing my own status and the Torah that I
represent and so on. So what am I supposed to do? אמר
ליה לשמעיה, Amar leih leshamayeih, he told his attendant, צא ואפרח עלי
בר אווזא, tzei ve'afrach alai bar avza, go like let a goose
loose in the court, okay. ושדי ליה עלוי, Veshadi leih alavai, you
know, and throw it on me. So there we are, she'll be
walking in, all of a sudden this goose will fly on me
as she's walking in. ואקום, Ve'akum, and then I'll have to get
ah this goose, and then I stood up in her presence. So
תוספות Tosafot has a good question. תוספות Tosafot says, תוספות Tosafot says,
I don't understand, says תוספות, Tosafot, the rising up we learn in
another גמרא Gemara has to be a rising up of respect. You
know, there are ways you could rise up to show that you're
mocking and disrespecting a person. The rising has to be in a
context of respect. So how did he satisfy it? So he's got
two answers. One answer is, she knew that he wanted a rise
in respect for her. She understood why the ruse was necessary, okay.
But the litigant, it protected the litigant, so the litigant didn't understand
the meaning of the rise and therefore the litigant didn't feel that
he was somehow being not fairly treated and it wouldn't impact his
sense of how he could present his case. So the ruse worked
for the litigant although the woman understood it. That's one explanation. The
other explanation is, you don't have to rise up if you're already
standing. So really this got him to rise up before she walked
in, and then he was already standing. Of course, if that was
really the case, why didn't he just say, "Oh, I think I
need to stretch," and then she walks in and then you're already
standing or something? So I don't know, maybe it would have been
the same. Okay. Now, the הגמרא Gemara says like this: והאמר מר
מחלוקת בשעת משא ומתן אבל בשעת גמר דין דברי הכל דיינים בישיבה
ובעלי דינין בעמידה. Veha'amar mar machloket besha'at masa umatan aval besha'at gmar
din divrei hakol dayanim biyishivah uva'alei dinin be'amidah. So we got a
problem, though. The problem is that when it comes to גמר דין,
gmar din, they have to stand and you have to sit. Okay.
So how can you be sitting? What are you going to do,
the duck thing again? So the goose thing again? Right? How are
you going to be sitting, you know, and she's going to be
standing, you know, wouldn't that also be an issue? She's standing and
then you should rise up as well? So the הגמרא Gemara says,
דיותיב כמאן דשרי מסאני. Deyotiv keman deshrei masanei. Yeah, you're sitting, but
you're sort of half standing. You're like sitting and you're sort of
like doing your, you know, your shoe, like you would be tying
your shoe, so you wouldn't be fully sitting, and therefore it would
be considered to be like appropriate. Okay. So, couldn't he just have
recused himself? I mean, it's so much of a... Yeah, but everybody
would have had to stand, whatever. Right. Because it's not because of
a specific relationship, right? Okay, so he's sticking this story of Rav
Huna's wife in between his comments from Rav Huna himself before. Right,
it was Rav Huna himself that said, oh, בשעת משא ומתן אבל
בשעת גמר דין. besha'at masa umatan aval besha'at gmar din. It's true.
He was directly one of the people involved in this whole discussion.
That's true. Oh, but you said he passed away before the story
of his wife. That's the way רשי Rashi explains it, right. Yeah,
yeah, right. So the הגמרא Gemara says okay. Okay. Now, ואמר איש
פלוני אתה זכאי איש פלוני אתה חייב. Ve'amar ish ploni atah zakai
ish ploni atah chayav. So as the judge is there, it's sort
of like my example of the yawning. Okay, there he is, he's
sort of sitting, but he's half out of his chair because he's
tying his shoe. So he's not really fully sitting, and then he's
passing the judgment. So you can sort of do that, even though
you know, as a big... again, it's a little funny because is
that a way of rising to show respect? Anyway, okay. Now the...
yes, on top of that... yeah, well here we learned on a
previous דף daf that a woman can't be a... right, that also
is nice. עדות? eidut? Right. And here we're getting the כבוד kavod
to her. Right. Well, that was very nice. We mentioned in passing
that a woman could be a litigant, and here we're actually illustrating
that. Right. Right, with all this honor being given to her. Right.
Okay, אמר רבה בר רב הונא האי צורבא מרבנן ועם הארץ דאית
להו דינא בהדי הדדי. Amar Rabbah bar Rav Huna hai tzurba merabbanan
ve'am ha'aretz de'it lehu dina bahadi hadadei. So we're going to continue
with this issue about respecting Torah and at the same time equal
treatment. So a certain student of the rabbis and a person who's
like, you know, a layperson, whatever, not a Torah scholar, that have
a court case together, so they're litigants. מותבינא ליה לצורבא מרבנן ולאם
הארץ נמי אמרינן ליה תיב. Motvina lei letzurba merabbanan vela'am ha'aretz nami
amrinan lei tiv. We allow the תלמיד חכם talmid chacham to sit
and we tell the עם הארץ am ha'aretz you also sit. Okay,
now it's a slightly different, like one we sort of like actually
we seat him, we walk him over and we put him into
"here, you sit here," and the other one we say, "you know,
you can sit too." Okay, so it's a little different, but anyway,
but so let's keep on seeing where this goes. ואי קאי לית
לן בה. Ve'i kai leit lan bah. Now if the, if the
non-תלמיד חכם talmid chacham wants to stand and he wants to stand
out of respect for the fact that his litigant is a תלמיד
חכם, talmid chacham, we don't insist that he sit, you know, in
order to, you know, you know, in order to enforce that sense
of like equal treatment. Did you suggest that they're talking about הידור?
hidur? Yeah, that's what I said. Okay, maybe I wasn't being clear.
No, the עם הארץ am ha'aretz person is standing presumably as a
way of giving respect or something to the learned person. Why else...
that's the way I'm understanding, why else is he standing, right? So
we don't insist to enforce the equality and say, "No, everybody in
this court does the same, he's sitting, you sit too." We... we
sort of tell him you can sit, but if he because of
his respect for the other one chooses to stand, we don't enforce
it. Okay, so we allow him to make that choice even though
it sort of puts him in the less respect... like, you know,
in the weaker position. All right, here I am, I have to
deal with a court case against some, you know, my... I don't
know, whoever it is, you know, my... my boyhood, you know, idol
or whatever, you know, this great sports person or whatever, so I'm
like, how do I act in front of that person, right? So
anyway, but it's interesting, like, because you would think maybe we have
to proactively work to try to enforce this equality. But actually, given
that this guy, the other guy's a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, you
want to stand, we'll let you stand. Okay, okay. Now the הגמרא
Gemara says like this, where were we? אמר... לית לן בה. Amar...
leit lan bah. רב בר שרביא הוה ליה דינא קמי דרב פפא.
Rav bar Sharvaya havah lei dina kammai deRav Pappa. So this רב
בר שרביא Rav bar Sharvaya had a case in front of רב
פפא. Rav Pappa. So this רב בר שרוויא Rav Bar Sharvaya had
a case in front of רב פפא. Rav Papa. ואותבין נמי לבעל
דיניה, ve'otvin nammi l'ba'al dinei, so they had him sit and they
had his litigant sit. אתא שליחא דבי דינא, ata shlicha de'bei dina,
now the court attendant came, בטש ביה, batsh bei, he kicked the
guy who was the non-תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. He said, "What are
you doing sitting? You're not respectful to sit in the presence of
your litigant there." ולא אמר ליה רב פפא תיב, ve'lo amar lei
Rav Papa tiv, and רב פפא Rav Papa did not say, "No,
no, no, that's fine, he can sit." So this is worse, right?
The guy is not on his own deciding to stand, somebody a
court officer is telling him he has to stand. This is clearly
putting him in a disadvantaged position. And רב פפא Rav Papa did
not do anything to counterbalance that. So היכי עביד הכי, heichi avid
hachi, how did he do that? והא מסתתמן טענתיה, ve'ha mistatmen ta'anatei,
this causes his again his claims to be clogged up. So אמר
רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, so רב פפא Rav Papa said, מימר
אמר איהו ההוא, meimar amar ee-hu ha'ot, no, no, no, because he
said, "Look, I know that the judge told me that I could
sit, so I don't feel when this court officer came and kicked
me, I don't treat that as a different treatment from the court."
So why did he kick you? שליחא דלא מיפייס מיניה, shlicha de'lo
mifeis minei, yeah, he didn't like me, you know, so this officer
had something against me, but I understand that the court has given
me license to sit. Now that seems like a little walk in
a line because even if you know, even imagine that you actually
had a fight with this court officer and that's why he was
kicking you, at the end of the day you're standing and the
other guy is sitting. And you can't help making you sort of
you know be in a disadvantaged type of a mindset. Okay, so
it's interesting that they're not, I think they're not doing more to
enforce a greater equal treatment here. ואמר רבה בר אבוה, ve'amar Rabbah
bar Avuha, says רבה בר אבוה, Rabbah bar Avuha, האי צורבא מרבנן,
hai tzurba me'rabbanan, a student of the rabbis, ועם הארץ, ve'am ha'aretz,
that they have a case together, לא ליקדם צורבא מרבנן וליתיב. lo
lijkam tzurba me'rabbanan ve'leysev. The תלמיד חכם talmid chacham shouldn't go into
the courtroom before the case and sit down and you know and
what he's doing, he takes out his גמרא, Gemara, he's learning his
דף יומי Daf Yomi while he's waiting for the case to start.
משום דמיחזי כמאן דסדר ליה לדיניה mishum d'meichzei k'man d'sader lei l'dinei
because it'll the other guy will walk in and there he'll see
you know the rabbis are all part of the same like class
in social groups and whatever, right? So there you walk in and
there you see you know this big rabbi who's the court case
and this other guy who's a Torah student and they're sitting in
the same room and maybe they're you know making a few like
pleasant comments to one another, "Oh, what are you learning? Oh, תוספות?
Tosafot? Oh, בבא קמא? Bava Kamma? Oh, whatever." Okay. And then the
guy will walk in and he'll see it'll seem like there's this
whole little collusion going on, right? So he'll say, "You know he's
got an opportunity to present his case when I wasn't around." So
don't do that. It looks bad, the appearances are bad, stay out
of the room. ולא אמרן אלא דלא קביע ליה עידניה, ve'lo amarun
ela d'lo kavia lei idnei, but here is now again the interesting
counterbalance. But that's only if the judge and this litigant who's a
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham don't have a fixed time to actually learn
together. אבל קביע ליה עידניה, aval kavia lei idnei, if they have
a regular חברותא chavrusa together or whatever regular class together, he the
judge is the teacher, לית לן בה, leis lan bah, it's not
a problem. I don't know, because the guy will go, "Yeah, they're
talking but obviously they're talking because he's going for his גמרא Gemara
lesson." I don't know, you ask me, that's like that's even worse.
Like they have a real ongoing relationship as a rebbe and a
student and I think I'm going to now get a fair trial
here? The judge should recuse himself, I don't begin to understand that.
But I do have to tell you that this actually you know
played out, I know cases this played out, you know רבקה עליה
השלום, Rivka aleiha ha'shalom, you know she would accompany women to בית
דין beit din for a גט, get, for example. And it wouldn't
be even if the case wasn't one about like you know even
if it was a בית דין beit din that was really trying
to like do the right thing and protect the woman's rights or
whatever and you know and be very you know be very just
right and ישר, yashar, just just and ישר. yashar. Sometimes like you
know describes the case, she described the case or maybe it was
my wife accompanied a woman to a גט get and described this
case where you know she walks in with her ex-husband or they
came in on slightly separate times, it doesn't matter, and all of
the judges and this was like from a בית דין beit din
that everybody assumes is so perfect, you know, so great, and normally
it's probably infinitely greater than everything else that's around there. But you
know the husband walks in and he's through all the guys that
he knows from ישיבה yeshiva and they all start schmoozing and talking
and this and that and like you know so like how are
you supposed to feel in that case that you're going to be
like treated as an equal you know as an equal party? Alright,
so anyway, so let's just read one more line. Let's just get
to the two dots. מימר אמר בעידניה טריד יה, meimar amar b'idnei
tared ya, they're just doing their learning. Okay. ואמר רבה בר אבוה,
ve'amar Rabbah bar Avuha, האי צורבא מרבנן דידע בסהדותא, hai tzurba me'rabbanan
d'yada besahaduta, somebody knows testimony, וזילא ביה מילתא למיזל לבי דינא דזוטא
מיניה, ve'zila bei milta l'meizal l'vei dina d'zuta minei, but he's a
big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and now he has to go to
this court of like these פישערס, pishers, excuse me, you know, so
I'm not sure I'm allowed to say that online. Anyway, he has
to go to this court about these like these you know meager
דיינים dayanim that are like his student or his student's students like
and you know it's not honorable for him and to present himself
as a witness in front of judges who are at this lower
status than he is, okay. לא ליזיל, lo leizil, צנע, tzne, don't
go! Okay. So אמר רב ששת בריה דרב אידי, Amar Rav Sheshet
brei deRav Idi, אנן נמי תנינא, anan nami tanina, what's the basis
for this? Oh, because we taught similarly. מצא שק וקופה ואין דרכו
ליטול הרי זה לא יטול. Matza sako kupa v'ein darko litol harei
zeh lo yitol. If you find, you're walking in the street and
you find some dusty old bag that's been abandoned, it's worth a
whole two dollars, and it's like beneath you to bend down, you
know, it's a lost object, to bend down and pick it up.
So the best way to test it is would you pick it
up if it was yours? And if you wouldn't bother to pick
it up if it was yours, you don't have to pick it
up to return it. So even though through your passive action somebody
is losing money, right, the owner is going to actually not get
his objects back and lose his objects, you can be passive to
protect your honor even if it comes at the cost of somebody,
if it's passive as it comes at the cost of somebody else's
loss of money. Okay, that's basically an idea of כבוד הבריות, kevod
habriyot, human dignity trumping, you know, certain sort of like monetary aspects,
certain aspects of where there's a monetary implications for you protecting your
dignity. But what about capital crimes? Ah, so that's the next line
in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. והני מילי בממונא, V'hani mili b'mamona, but
that's when the only thing lost is some monetary issue. אבל באיסורא,
Aval b'issura, when it comes to transgressions, אין חכמה ואין תבונה ואין
עצה לנגד השם. ein chochma v'ein tvuna v'ein etza l'neged Hashem. There's
no wisdom or, you know, or whatever, or understanding, you know, you
know, in the presence of God. Meaning, I don't want any of
your חשבונות, cheshbonos, as we would say. Okay? If it's God's honor
at stake, it's a real violation, then כל מקום שיש חילול השם
אין חולקין כבוד לרב. kol makom sheyesh chilul Hashem ein cholkin kavod
l'rav. You don't care about honor when it comes to God's honor.
Now, what is the case? So David correctly said, oh, the parallel
case would be it's a capital crime. Okay. And I know testimony
relating to a capital crime. Okay. Now, one case would be if
I don't say something, this guy's going to get punished. That's not
about necessarily כבוד השם. kavod Hashem. That's not about a violation. That's
about protecting somebody from actual physical injury. He's going to get lashes,
he's going to get executed. But let's say it's the flip. Let's
say the person did a violation and I know they did a
violation. Okay, that is where it's almost protecting God's honor because God's
honor has been violated, somebody did a transgression, and you're coming now
to defend God's honor as it were, to testify about the violation
and get this guy punished. But you know what? It seems a
little still funny because we're talking about a punishment after the fact.
Right? That's a little bit different than protecting God's honor like protecting,
stopping an עבירה aveira from being committed, right? So, you know, so
רש״י Rashi says, רש״י Rashi reads it a different way. רש״י Rashi
reads it that we're no longer talking about a witness. You're sitting
in a court case, your רבי rebbi is the judge, you're there
as some, you know, as some like, what's it called, not intern,
what are those called, the people who work for the justices? Clerk!
Or whatever. You're the clerk. And the judge is about to פסקן,
pasken, let's say, for this woman that, I don't know, that she
can go ahead and her husband is dead and she can remarry.
And you know that that's a wrong judgment and that this woman
is now about to commit adultery because her husband really is alive
or whatever. You have to speak up, even though you're going to
be overriding your רבי rebbi who was the judge, you cannot give
respect to your רבי rebbi and you have to speak up to
protect an עבירה aveira from being done. So there are actually three
scenarios. רש״י Rashi gives the easiest scenario: You don't respect a רבי
rebbi or whatever, you don't give honor to the Torah, you know,
when it's going to lead to an עבירה aveira being done. You
have to act and speak up. You don't care about honor to
your רבי. rebbi. Okay. The other scenarios which are more likely the
parallel in the גמרא Gemara is about whether you are choosing to
not testify. So in the case where somebody is going to be
executed or lashed, obviously you have to testify. But that's just not
just because of honor to God, that's because of protecting human life,
you know, and protecting whatever. That's different than protecting money, right? Protecting
somebody from bodily injury that they don't deserve. It's the, so the
interesting case is do you have to speak up if it's beneath
your dignity as a rabbi to go to the court, if somebody
is not going to get punished for a sin that they've done?
Right? Is there a sense of protecting God's honor that obligates me
to lower myself to go to this court in order to ensure
that this guy gets punished for an עבירה? aveira? You know, I
think some part of us feels once the sin has been done,
like to feel that that's included in protecting God's honor to make
sure that the guy gets punished feels like of a different quality
than of preventing a sin from being done in the first place.
Okay, we will end with this. Yes. I have personally an interesting...